Even nature's most disgusting creatures
حتى أقبح المخلوقات في الطبيعة
have important secrets,
لديها أسرار مهمة ،
but who would want a swarm of cockroaches
لكن من يريد سرباً من الصراصير
coming towards them?
أن يقترب منه ؟
Yet one of the greatest differences between natural and human technologies
أعظم الفروقات بين الطبيعة وتكنولوجيا البشر
relates to robustness.
تُنسب إلى المتانة .
Robust systems are stable in complex
نظام المتانة ثابت في البيئات المعقدة
and new environments.
والجديدة .
Remarkably, cockroaches can self-stabilize
بشكل بارز ، تقدر الصراصير على الثبات
running over rough terrain.
أثناء الجري على مناطق وعرة .
When we put a jet pack on them,
عندما وضعنا عليهم حقيبة نفاثة ،
or give them a perturbation like an earthquake,
أو أحدثنا لهم اهتزاز مثل الزلزال ،
we discovered that their wonderfully tuned legs
اكتشفنا أنهم بأعجوبة يثنون أقدامهم
allow them to self-stabilize
لتسمح لهم بتثبيت أنفسهم
without using any of their brainpower.
بدون استخدام أي مجهود عصبي .
They can go over complex terrain like grass,
يستطيعون المشي فوق سطح معقد مثل العشب ،
no problem, and not get destabilized.
بلا مشكلة ، وبدون أن يختل توازنهم .
We discovered a new behavior where,
اكتشفنا سلوك جديد حيث ،
because of their shape,
أنه وبسبب شكلهم ،
they actually roll automatically to their side
أنهم يلتفون تلقائياً إلى جانبهم
to go through this artificial test bit of grass.
ليجتازون اختبار العشب الصناعي .
Robust systems can perform multiple tasks
أنظمة متينة تستطيع تأدية عدة مهام
with the same structure.
بنفس التركيب .
Here's a new behavior we've discovered.
هنا سلوك جديد قمنا باكتشافه .
The animals rapidly invert and disappear
هذه الكائنات تنقلب بسرعة وتختفي
in less than 150 milliseconds — you never see them —
في أقل من 150 جزء من الثانية ، ولا تراها أبداً ،
using the same structures that they use to run, their legs.
باستخدام نفس الأعضاء التي تساعدها في الجري ، أقدامها .
They can run upside down
تستطيع الجري مقلوبة رأساً على عقب
very rapidly on rods, branches and wires,
وبسرعة هائلة على القضبان ، الأغصان والأسلاك ،
and if you perturb one of those branches,
واذا قمت بتحريك واحد من تلك الأغصان ،
they can do this.
يستطيعون عمل هذا .
They can perform gymnastic maneuvers
يقومون بحركات بهلاوانية
like no robot we have yet.
لا يشبهها أي روبوت حتى الآن .
And they have nearly unlimited
كما أن لديها عدد لا محدود تقريباً
maneuverability with that same structure
من تلك الحركات باستخدام نفس التركيب
and unprecedented access to a variety
ومنفذ لا مثيل له لمجموعة
of different areas.
مختلفة من المناطق .
They have wings for flying when they get warm,
تمتلك أجنحة للطيران عندما تشعر بالحر ،
but they use those same wings to flip over
كما أنها أيضاً تستخدم تلك الأجنحة للإنقلاب
if they get destabilized.
في حال تعرضها لعدم التوازن .
Very effective.
فعالة جداً .
Robust systems are also fault tolerant and fail-safe.
أنظمة متينة أيضاً ممتصة للصدمات وآمنة في السقوط .
This is the foot of a cockroach.
هذه هي رجل الصرصور .
It has spines, gluey pads and claws,
لها أشواك ، وسائد لاصقة ومخالب ،
but if you take off those feet,
حتى لو خلعت هذه الأرجل ،
they can still go over rough terrain,
لا يزال بإمكانها المشي على الأسطح الخشنة ،
like the bottom video that you see,
كما ترون في الفيديو السفلي ،
without hardly slowing down. Extraordinary.
بدون أن تبطئ من سرعتها ، غير عادية .
They can run up mesh without their feet.
تستطيع أيضاً أن تتسلق شبكة بلا أرجل .
Here's an animal using a normal, alternating tripod:
هنا ترون كائن يستخدم قوائمه الثلاثة الطبيعية البديلة :
three legs, three legs, three legs,
ثلاثة أرجل ، ثلاثة أرجل ، ثلاثة أرجل ،
but in nature, the insects often have lost their legs.
لكن في الطبيعة ، هذه الحشرات غالباً ما تفقد أرجلها .
Here's one moving with two middle legs gone.
هنا ترون آخر يتحرك بعد فقدان أرجله الوسطى .
It can even lose three legs, in a tripod,
يمكن أن يفقد حتى ثلاثة أرجل ، في ثلاثي القوائم ،
and adopt a new gait, a hopping gait.
ويطور مشية جديدة ، مشية عرجاء .
And I point out that all of these videos
وأنبه إلى أن هذه الفيدوهات
are slowed down 20 times,
تمت تبطئتها 20 مرة ،
so they're actually really fast, when you see this.
بالتالي هم بالفعل سريعون جداً ، عندما ترى هذا .
Robust systems are also damage resistant.
أنظمة متينة مقاومة أيضاً للصدمات .
Here's an animal climbing up a wall.
هنا كائن يتسلق الحائط .
It looks like a rapid, smooth, vertical climb,
يبدو تسلق سريع ، مريح وعمودي ،
but when you slow it down,
لكن عندما تقوم بتبطئته ،
you see something very different.
ترى شئ مختلف تماماً .
Here's what they do.
إليكم ما يفعلونه .
They intentionally have a head-on collision with the wall
يقومون عمداً ورؤوسهم للأعلى بالاصطدام بالحائط
so they don't slow down and can transition up it
بدون أن يقللون من سرعتهم يستطيعون الانتقال عليه
in 75 milliseconds.
في 75 جزء من الثانية .
And they can do this in part because they have
يستطيعون فعل ذلك بسهولة لأن لديهم
extraordinary exoskeletons.
هياكل خارجية غير اعتيادية .
And they're really just made up of compliant joints
مصممة كلياً من مفاصل متوافقة
that are tubes and plates
عبارة عن صفائح و أنابيب
connected to one another.
متصلة ببعضها البعض .
Here's a dissection of an abdomen of a cockroach.
هنا ترون تشريح لبطن صرصور .
You see these plates, and you see the compliant membrane.
ترون الصفائح ، والغشاء المتوافق معها .
My engineering colleague at Berkeley
زميلي المهندس في بيركيلي
designed with his students
صمم مع تلاميذه
a novel manufacturing technique
تقنية صناعية بارعة
where you essentially origami the exoskeleton,
حيث قام مبدئياً بصنع الهيكل الخاريجي مثل الأوريغامي
you laser cut it, laminate it,
قطعه بأشعة الليزر ، لمّعه ،
and you fold it up into a robot.
وبعدها قام بثنيه على شكل روبوت .
And you can do that now in less than 15 minutes.
وتستطيع القيام بذلك الآن في أقل من 15 دقيقة .
These robots, called DASH,
هذه الروبوتات ، تدعى داش (DASH)
for Dynamic Autonomous Sprawled Hexapod,
اختصار لـ ( ديناميكية ذاتية متمددة سداسية الأرجل ) ،
are highly compliant robots,
روبوتات عالية المرونة ،
and they're remarkably robust as a result
ومتينة بشكل ملحوظ نتيجة
of these features.
لهذه الخصائص .
They're certainly incredibly damage resistant.
كما أنها بالتأكيد مضادة للصدمات .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
They even have some of the behaviors of the cockroaches.
كما أن لديها أيضاً بعض من سلوك الصاصير .
So they can use their smart, compliant body
فتستطيع باستخدام أجسادها الذكية والمرنة
to transition up a wall
أن تتنقل على الحائط
in a very simple way.
بطريقة بسيطة جداً .
They even have some of the beginnings
لديها أيضاً بعض من بدائيات
where they disappear.
سلوك الإنقلاب السريع
Now we want to know why they can go anywhere.
والآن نريد أن نعرف لماذا يتواجدون في كل الأمكنة .
three-millimeter gaps,
لقد اكتشفنا أنهم يستطيعون الدخول
the height of two pennies, two stacked pennies,
بارتفاع عملتين معدنية ، عملتين متلاصقتين ،
and when they do this,
وعندما يفعلون ذلك ،
at high speeds,
وبسرعة عالية ،
although you never see it.
وبالرغم من ذلك لا تراهم أبداً .
To understand it better,
ولفهم ذلك بشكل أفضل ،
and showed that they can compress their body
وأظهرت أنهم يستطيعون ضغط أجسادهم
by over 40 percent.
بنسبة تفوق الـ 40 % .
We put them in a materials testing machine
وقد وضعناهم في جهاز لاختبار المواد
to look at the stress strain analysis
لنرى ماهو تحليل جهد الضغط
and showed that they can withstand forces
وقد أظهرت أنها تستطيع تحمل ضغط
800 times their body weight,
800 ضعف وزنها ،
and after this they can fly and run
وبعد ذلك تستطيع الطيران والجري
absolutely normally.
بطريقة عادية جداً .
So you never know where
أن لا تعلمون أبداً إلى أين
curiosity-based research will lead,
يقود البحث المبني على الفضول ،
and someday you may want a swarm
وقد تودون يوماً أن ترون سرباً
of cockroach-inspired robots
من الروبوتات المستلهمة من الصراصير
to come at you.
أن تأتي إليكم .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Thank you.
شكراً لكم .
(Applause)
( تصفيق )